我要来点音乐 把吹笛子的女孩儿带上来
I want music. Bring the flute girl.
她闹肚子痛了 女主人
Down with the gripes, domina.
那就换弹七弦琴的吧
The lyre player, then.
他在上次牧神节的时候死掉了 女主人
He died the last Lupercalia, domina.
我一直在找替补的
I have been looking for a replacement,
不过近来他们的价格太高了
but they are very expensive at the moment.
那就一点音乐也没有？
There's no music at all?
阿尔泰亚很会唱歌
Althea sings well.
是吗？
Does she?
阿尔泰亚 唱点什么
Althea, sing something.
我不会…
I don't...
别嘀咕了 你会唱《萨福的王冠》吗？
Don't mumble. Do you know Crown Of Sappho?
是的 女主人
Yes, domina.
哦 那就来吧
Well, go on, then.
救救我
Help me.
毒药 一定是毒药
Poison. It must have been.
- 你不是吧 - 当然是 我发誓
- You didn't. - I did. I swear.
爸爸的一个信使
One of father's litter bearers.
就跟动物一样滑稽 那玩意儿跟马一样大
It was beastly fun. Penis like a horse.
嘘 我不想你把妈妈吵醒了
I don't want to wake mother.
我不明白你为什么那么怕她
I don't know why you're so scared of her.
- 我看她还是挺善良的嘛 - 你不了解她
- She seems harmless enough to me. - You don't know her.
什么声音？
What was that?
不
No.
母亲
Mother!
- 奥克塔维娅 - 天哪
- Octavia. - Gods.
她名字叫什么？
What's her name again?
伊俄卡斯特
Jocasta.
她对你没什么好处
She's a bad influence.
哎 我说
Oh, I say.
你在干什么？这是谁啊？
What are you doing? Who is this?
某个想要毒杀我的仆人
One of the servants tried to poison me.
你对仆人们干了什么
What have you been doing to the servants that they want to murder you?
逼得他们想杀你？没什么 这都是赛维莉娅的阴谋
Nothing. This is Servilia's work.
安东尼一走 她就以为能为所欲为了
With Antony gone, she thinks she can just do as she pleases.
如果你知道是她做的 那干吗还要折磨他
If you know it's her, why are you torturing him?
因为得要先拷打 招供才算有法律效力
Because it isn't a legal confession unless there's torture.
你要把赛维莉娅告上法庭？
You must take Servilia to court.
不 我要杀了她
No, I'm gonna kill her.
如果我为此被带上法庭 我就可以名正言顺地声称是正当防卫
If I get taken to court for it, I can always claim it was self-defense.
我把后路都铺好了 明白吗？
I'm thinking ahead, you see?
这简直是大错特错 我都不知道从何说起了
This is wrong in so many ways I don't know where to start.
那你想要我干什么？
Well, what would you have me do?
我不动手 那谁来保护我们
Who would protect us if I didn't?
我…我要… 如果你不介意的话
I... I'm... If you don't mind.
不 别走 我需要你做第三方的证人
No, don't go. I need you as an independent witness.
把她带走吧
Take her away.
泰门 难道这要折腾一整夜吗？
Timon, is this gonna take all night?
他又昏过去了 弄醒他
He's out again. Bring him round.
等等
Wait.
告诉我名字 小子
Give me a name, boy.
告诉我名字 我就饶了你
Give me a name and I will spare your life.
你想活下去 对不对？
You want to live, don't you?
那就告诉我 保住你的小命
Tell me, then. For your life.
是赛维莉娅
Servilia.
赛维莉娅
看 没那么困难 对吧
There, that wasn't so hard, was it?
等你杀了他之后
After you've killed him,
小心处理尸体
dispose of the body discreetly.
饶恕我吧 我不知道那孩子被收买了
Forgive me. I did not know that boy was corrupt.
如果必要 我愿意献出生命
I will take my life if I must,
但请相信我是忠心耿耿的
but please know that I've been faithful.
该死的血迹 弄脏了我的裙子
Damn blood. It'll stain my dress.
我被骗了 还让您这么失望
I was misled and I failed you miserably.
您要愿意就惩罚我吧
Punish me as you see fit.
把你阉了都不为过
It would serve you right to be gelded.
如您所愿 女主人
As you wish, domina.
我当然愿意 你知道吗 要不是我觉得阉人太不体面…
And I would, you know, if eunuchs were not so unfashionable.
让我们把这一切都忘了吧
Let's just forget about the whole thing.
感激不尽 女主人 感激不尽
Thank you, domina. Thank you.
起来 你这蠢人
Just get up, you silly man.
下次你想找个男孩 去集市上买一个就行了
Next time you want a boy, buy one at the market.
谁都知道不该从街上捡一个回来
Any fool knows not to pick one up from the streets.
谢谢你 女主人
Thank you, domina.
走吧
Go.
给我拿点面包和奶酪来
And bring me some bread and cheese.
我简直快要饿死了
I'm absolutely starving.
- 你叫什么名字 朋友？- 我不是你朋友
- What's your name, friend? - I'm not your friend.
人有权知道杀死自己的人的名字
A man's got a right to know the name of his murderer.
泰门
Timon.
你是个犹太人 对吧
You're a Jew, ain't you?
- 那是个犹太人的名字 - 那是我在生意上用的名字
- That's not a Jew name. - That's my name for business purposes.
- 听着 泰门 - 啊 别劳神了
- Listen, Timon... - Don't bother.
赛维莉娅 她也很富有 跟你女主人一样
Servilia, she's as rich as your woman there.
如果你放了我 她会好好报答你的
She'll pay you good money if you spare me.
哈 我可不信 你现在对她还有什么用处？
Well, I doubt it. What good are you to her now?
她很喜欢我 事实上 她爱我
She's very fond of me. She loves me, practically.
她爱我
She loves me.
那我希望她早点忘记好了
Well, I expect she'll get over it.
我们到了
Here we are.
求求你 我自己也有点钱
Please, I have money of my own.
任何价格我都愿意给
I'll pay you whatever.
求求你别杀我
Please, don't kill me.
我求求你 我才16岁
Please, I beg you. I'm only 16.
我们今晚干完了 头儿？我家里还有女人等着呢
We done for tonight, boss? I've got a woman waiting.
是的 我们做完了
Yes. We're done.
那再见喽
See you later, then.
别听你叔叔的 他在开玩笑
Don't listen to your uncle. He's teasing.
闭上你的嘴 把你的嘴堵起来好了
Close your mouth, please. Put your mouth away, please.
谢谢你了 这可太无礼了
That was really, really nice. Thank you so much.
主啊 愿你保佑我们
Lord, protect us.
出了什么事？
What has happened?
没事 公事而已
Nothing. Business.
公事？你至少也该
Business? Can you not at least
在回家前把你的公事洗掉吧
wash off your business before returning home?
为什么？我可不觉得羞耻
Why? I'm not ashamed of it.
孩子们 到外面去玩吧
Children, go and play outside.
- 给我站住 - 兄弟
- Stay where you are. - Brother...
我才是他们的爸爸 又不是你
I'm their father, not you.
用不着你来管教我的孩子
You don't tell my children what to do.
走
Go.
走啊
Go!
没事的 宝贝 爸爸只是累了
It's all right, babies. Papa's just tired.
怎么？
What?
说出来啊 告诉我
Speak, then. Tell me.
看看你自己
Look at yourself.
看看你都变成什么了 你是只野兽
Look at what you have become. You are an animal.
我正直的兄弟啊
My righteous brother.
他有没有告诉你 在朱迪亚时他"高尚"的生活？
Did he tell you of his righteous life back in Judea?
你跟她提过了吗 兄弟？
Did you tell her about that, brother?
我已经变了
I've changed my ways.
小偷小摸 赌钱玩女人
Thieving, gambling, chasing whores.
- 够了 - 这可是真相啊
- Stop it. - It's the truth.
你现在又要说真相了？
Are you going to start speaking the truth now?
我会洗耳恭听的
Because that I would find interesting!
不说是吧 我谅你也不会说
No? I didn't think so.
她该过更好的生活
She deserves better.
那可太糟糕了 她有的就只有这些
Too bad for her, then. This is what she's got.
你替那个罗马女巫干的这些龌龊勾当
These treacheries you do for that Roman witch,
她有好好补偿你吗？
does she pay you enough?
我得到我所需要的了
I get what I need.
她一定是金银珠宝收买你了
She must lavish you with jewels and gold.
我的兄弟该富得流油了
What a rich man my brother is.
告诉我 你把那堆难以想象的财富藏哪儿了？
Tell me, where do you hide such fantastic wealth?
我们不都是替这些人卖命么
We both sell what we have to these people.
就算罗马全部的财富也不足以让我 出卖天主赐予的一切
All Rome's wealth is not enough to buy what Ha-Shem has given me.
又来说天主了
Again with Ha-Shem.
让天主替我养家糊口啊
Let Ha-Shem make me a living.
那个女巫给我的钱买下了这座该死的房子
The money that witch pays me bought this fucking house,
这张该死的桌子 还有我老婆身上穿的该死的裙子
this fucking table, and that fucking dress my wife wears!
- 这能让你觉得自豪 - 跟任何自由的罗马人一样自豪
- That makes you proud? - Proud as any free Roman.
你可以呼吸这充满恶臭的罗马空气
You breathe this fetid air of Rome,
但你不是罗马人
but you are not Roman.
你可以在这污秽的街道上昂首阔步
You walk her beshitted streets, you speak her mongrel language,
可以说着这四不象的语言 可你不是罗马人 你是犹太人
but you're not Roman. You're a Jew.
你可以不记得 但他们不会
You may forget that, they never will.
你说得太多 知道的太少
You speak so much and know so little.
看着我
Look at me.
难道你憎恨这个名字到这个地步 以致于要自取其辱吗？
Do you hate your name so much to invite this shame?
考虑一下你的家族
Think of your family.
看着我
Look at me!
动手啊 来啊 动手打我啊
Try it, come on! Try it! Hit me!
打我啊
Hit me!
原来如此
That's it. Not so easy to beat me anymore, is it?
要揍我不像以前那么容易了 是吧 我再也不是你的小兄弟了
I'm not your little brother anymore.
叶什 叶什
Yesh. Yesh!
在北方 伟大的军团
In the north, the great army
在将军们的率领下 希尔提乌斯和潘撒将军
under the leadership of the generals Hirtius and Pansa
在凯撒·屋大维的协助下
assisted by Caesar Octavian
即将与叛军开战
is about to engage with the forces of the traitor
马克·安东尼的叛军
Mark Antony.
所有的公民都被要求
All citizens are requested to make offerings
为我们英雄士兵的凯旋奉上献礼
for the success of our heroic soldiers.
共和国万岁
Long live the Republic!
[穆提那 阿尔卑斯山南麓　高卢]
好好排队
Get into line now!
乌瑞纳斯
Vorenus.
泰特斯·波罗？
Titus Pullo?
别告诉我你是负责清理战场的
Well, don't tell me you've taken up scavenging.
是谁？
Who's that?
你认不出我了 波罗？
Do you not know me, Pullo?
是你啊 小主人
Is that you, young master?
没问题的
It's fine.
我们是老朋友了
We're old friends.
屋大维
Octavian.
波罗 他们现在叫我凯撒
They call me Caesar now, Pullo.
都长成大人了 就知道你有这个能耐
All grown up. Always knew you had it in you.
这么说你打赢了
You won, then?
看起来是
So it seems.
怎么赢的？我无意冒犯
How? I mean no offense.
大多数不是我的功劳
I can't take much credit.
都是希尔提乌斯和潘撒手下士兵的战绩
The legions under Hirtius and Pansa did heroic work.
剩下的要归功于阿格里帕
The rest I owe to Agrippa.
怎样都好 祝贺你
Anyroad, congratulations.
谢谢 你怎么来这儿了 波罗？
Thank you. What brings you here, Pullo?
从外表上看你并没有投身战斗
You didn't take part in the fighting either from the look of you.
乌瑞纳斯跟着安东尼一起离开了罗马
Vorenus left Rome with Antony.
我希望赶在开战前找到他
I hoped to find him before the battle started.
我来是为了告诉他 他孩子没死
I came to tell him that his children are not dead.
可现在我还得看看 他自己是不是已经死了
But now I must see if he is dead himself.
那我们一定要找到他
We must find him, then.
我会让掌兵官亲自在伤员里查找的
I'll have my tribunes personally search among the wounded.
谢谢 我本来没期望…
Thank you. I can hardly expect...
废话 要是你在这儿找不到他 你应该去阿尔卑斯山南边找找
Nonsense. If you don't find him here, you'd do well to comb the Cisalpine hills.
安东尼和他的人躲在那里
Antony and his men have skulked off there.
信使
Courier.
沿着路向北
Take the road north.
如果有人胆敢拦路
Should anyone challenge your passage
你就给他们看看凯撒的印记
you show them the seal of Caesar.
让他们想想后果
Warn them of the consequences.
你需要一些新鲜的干粮和一匹最快的马
You'll need fresh rations and a fast horse.
阿格里帕的人会帮你处理的
Agrippa's men will see to it.
谢谢您 阁下
Thank you, sir.
哦 征服者们回来了？
The conquering heroes return.
又想出什么好诗了 米西纳斯？
Another brilliant poem, Maecenas?
你就没什么要紧的事做了？
Is there not something useful you might do?
没有歌谣来传颂 胜利就不成其为胜利
Victory is not victory until it has a song.
希尔提乌斯和潘撒身边的医生有什么消息吗？
What news from the medics on Hirtius and Pansa?
怕是快要咽气了 两个都是
Dead of their wounds, I'm afraid, both of them.
可怜的人
Poor souls.
拥抱着他们的荣誉死去
To die in the hour of their glory.
嗯 是很伤感
Very sad.
不过 倒方便了
But convenient.
现在战绩全是我们的了
The victory is now ours alone.
坦白说 这结果再好不过了
Couldn't have worked out better, frankly.
你倒是给那个老恶棍狠狠上了一课啊
You really taught that old bully a proper lesson.
这与个人恩怨无关
It was not a personal matter.
为了共和国 这是必要的
It was necessary for the good of the Republic.
当然 当然
Of course. Of course.
阿格里帕 我有几封信 需要你带去罗马
Agrippa, I've got letters I'm going to want you to take on ahead to Rome.
第一封带给我姐姐
The first goes to my sister.
奥克塔维娅？
Octavia?
我只有那一个姐姐 阿格里帕
I only have the one sister, Agrippa.
确保直接把信交到她手里
Make sure you put it directly into her hand.
我母亲有偷信的习惯
My mother has a habit of stealing mail.
再来是给西赛罗的
The next goes to Cicero.
为什么要叫个将军去干信使的活儿？
Why send a general to do a courier's work?
没关系 我很乐意去
That's all right. I am happy to go.
我要西赛罗庆祝我的凯旋
I'm asking Cicero for a triumph.
只有阿格里帕在人家才会当真 他看上去是那么…
He'll know I'm serious if Agrippa is there looking...
英勇而严肃
grim and soldierly.
我真希望你叫他们吹的时候离远点
I wish you would tell them to do that further away.
每次都吓我一跳
It gives me a fright every time.
你的军队已经集结完毕
Your troops are gathering.
是时候跟他们训话了
Time to give them a speech.
是啊 你觉得该用哪篇演讲辞？
Right. Which speech do you think?
嗯 就用要钱的那篇
The one about money.
先生们 我们的活儿干得不错
Gentlemen...
我们已经获得了胜利
we have done our work well.
那将永载史册
We have gained a victory that will live on in history forever.
我们已经拯救了共和国
We have saved the Republic
击退了对她的威胁
from those who threatened her.
罗马现在可是欠着我们呢
Rome is now in our debt.
我们该拿到 一大笔钱
And we are owed a great deal of money.
正当安东尼拉着他的残兵败将
So while Antony drags the remnants of his men
退回北方的冰封之地
to the frozen north,
我认为我们应该南下去罗马
I thought we might head south to Rome.
你们说呢？
What do you say?
是不是该让元老院好好犒劳我们？
Is it time to tell the Senate to pay up?
是 那好 去罗马
Well, then, to Rome!
- 战无不胜 - 万岁 万岁
- Mars! Mars! - Exulte! Exulte!
乌瑞纳斯？
Vorenus?
我在找乌瑞纳斯
I'm looking for Prefect Vorenus.
我出一袋盐给帮助我的人
A bag of salt for any man that helps me.
卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
Lucius Vorenus.
我在找卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
I'm looking for Lucius Vorenus.
乌瑞纳斯？
Vorenus?
你来这儿干什么？
What are you doing here?
你的孩子们还活着
Your children are alive.
把他抬到那边去 小子们
Take him over there, lads.
搬到那边去
Move it on up there.
第八步兵队损失了整整两个小队
Eighth Cohort lost two full maniples.
第九步兵队 差不多全完了 第十队无人伤亡
Ninth, almost wiped out. Tenth Cohort intact.
第四军团情况更糟 长官
The Fourth Legion's much worse, sir.
他们直接承受了所有的攻势
They suffered the full brunt of the attack.
是的 是的
Yes, yes.
总共死了多少？
How many dead in total?
8000人 长官 或多或少
8,000 men, sir, give or take.
8000？
8,000?
噢 打起精神来 你不还活着吗？难道不是吗？
Oh, do cheer up. You're still alive, aren't you?
我希望是 如果这就是冥界 那还真够叫人失望的
I do hope so. If this is the afterlife, it is extremely disappointing.
解散第四步兵队
Disband the Fourth Cohort
让生还者补充到第三步兵队
and use the survivors to reinforce the Third.
我们去北方
We're heading north.
我要搭建起一座营地 第一场雪前就得在山上盖好
I want to establish a base camp in the mountain before the first snowfall.
遵命 长官
Yes, sir.
还有 掌兵官 别老是拉长着脸
And, Tribune, don't look so damn grim.
- 做出表率来 - 是 长官
- Set an example. - Yes, sir.
- 抱歉 长官 - 你可以走了
- Sorry, sir. - Off you go.
你在那儿干什么啊？你是帮我缝伤口还是在做裙子
What are you doing back there?
你动作就不能快点啊
You stitching me up or making a dress? Will you hurry up, man?
在山上扎营 这主意妥当吗？
A base camp in the mountains, is that wise?
啊 伯斯卡将军发话了 你有更好的主意吗？
General Posca speaks. Do you have a better idea?
趁我们看上去手里还有军队
While we still have the semblance of an army,
我想我们应该缔结和约
I would've thought we should offer terms.
和约？投降条约？
Terms? Of surrender?
听你个奴隶放屁
That's fucking slave talk.
不 我们不需要这个
No, we will have no more of that.
那就上山吧 然后呢？
North to the mountains, then. And after that?
我会想出办法的
I'll think of something.
啊 该死的
God damn it, man!
- 安东尼将军 长官 - 啊 乌瑞纳斯
- General Antony, sir. - Vorenus.
请求允许我离队 长官
Requesting permission to leave the legion, sir.
这才是真正的士兵
Now that is a real soldier for you.
多数人都趁夜逃走了
Most men just slip away into the night.
可这个人
But this one,
在他抛弃我之前还来征求同意
he asks permission before he deserts me.
那么 有什么事？
Well, what is it?
是关于我的孩子 长官
It's my children, sir.
他们还活着 被抓去当奴隶了
They're alive and in slavery.
既是好消息 也是坏消息 呃?
Good news, bad news.
我得去找他们 长官
I must find them, sir.
好吧
All right.
今天我已经失去了不少好士兵
The number of good men I've lost today,
再多一个也没什么大不了
one more isn't gonna make any difference.
多谢 长官
Thank you, sir.
你们俩 等等!
One more thing, boys!
一定要告诉所有你们遇到的人
Be sure to tell everyone you meet
马克·安东尼并没有战败
that Mark Antony is not defeated.
他会回来的
He will return,
那些违抗他的人 都将付出代价
and all those that defied him shall pay!
那个该死的小杂碎屋大维
That fucking little brat Octavian
他将会是第一个
shall be first!
听到了吗?
You hear me, boys?
遵命 长官
Will do, chief.
帕塔拉递过话来
Word from Patara.
他们已经答应我们的要求了 送来了16 000塔兰特
They've capitulated to our demands. They send 16,000 talents.
- 多少军队？- 7000
- How many troops? - 7000.
利西亚那边呢？
And Lycia?
还没有回音 但我想他们会效仿的
No word as yet, but I imagine they will follow suit.
嗯 务必保证他们会归降 阿门
See that they do.
现在我们应该有8个军团了
We must be up to eight legions now.
是9个 25000名步兵
Nine. 25,000 infantry,
10000骑兵
10,000 cavalry.
差不多和安东尼实力相当了
Almost a match for Antony.
好
It's good.
非常好
It's very good.
您看上去容光焕发
Well, you look magnificent.
正是适合画肖像
You should have your portrait done.
不用了 没时间做这些表面文章了
No, no time for such vanity.
会让你妈妈开心的
It would please your mother.
确实如此 不是吗？
It would, wouldn't it?
圣洁蒙福的女神
O holy and blessed lady,
人类永远的慰藉
perpetual comfort of humankind,
您的慷慨和仁慈滋养着整个世界
who by thy bounty and grace nourishes the whole world,
您怜悯受难人的苦
and bears a great compassion to the troubles of the miserable
如同慈爱的母
as a loving mother would,
您是世间万物生身之母
you are she that is the natural mother of all things,
自然力量的主宰
the mistress and governess of all the elements,
您是天上诸神第一等
first of the gods celestial,
女神中的引路人
light of the goddesses.
圣洁蒙福的女神
O holy and blessed lady, perpetual comfort of humankind,
您的慷慨和仁慈滋养着整个世界
who by thy bounty and grace nourishes the whole world
您怜悯受难人的苦
and bears a great compassion to the troubles of the miserable
如同慈爱的母
as a loving mother would.
圣洁蒙福的女神
O holy and blessed lady,
人类永远的慰藉
perpetual comfort of humankind,
您的慷慨和仁慈滋养着整个世界
who by thy bounty and grace nourishes the whole world,
您怜悯受难人的苦
and bears a great compassion to the troubles of the miserable
如同慈爱的母
as a loving mother would,
您是世间万物生身之母
you are she who is the natural mother to all things,
自然力量的主宰
the mistress and the governess of all the elements.
你知道我为什么请你来 对吗？
You know why you're here, don't you?
阿提娅
Atia.
你的那个小鬼都招认了
Your boy confessed everything.
吓坏得话都说不出来了？
Are you too afraid to speak?
你得势的时候 可不是像现在这么安静？
You weren't so quiet when I was in your power.
你那时候口若悬河
You were very talkative then.
"缓慢而痛苦的死亡"
"A slow and painful death."
那是你说要赐予我的
That's what you promised me.
那也是你应得的
That's what you deserve.
你觉得自己高高在上 是吗？
You think you're so fucking superior, don't you?
你哪里知道我在想什么
You have no idea what I think.
是吗？愿闻其详
No? Well, tell me.
告诉我你在想什么
Tell me what you think.
我在想
I think...
你是个忧伤 寂寞的小动物
you're a sad, lonely little creature.
我想此时此刻
I think at this moment,
你的恐惧比我的深
you're more afraid than I am.
我这辈子还从没像现在这么高兴
I've never been happier in my life.
那你为何还喋喋不休？
Then why do you keep talking?
杀了我
Kill me.
当你亲吻我的脚趾
When you kiss my feet
哀求我结束你的痛苦的时候
and beg for me to end your suffering,
我会杀了你的
then I'll kill you.
有什么手段都使出来吧
Do as you like.
泰门
Timon.
你觉得你现在羞辱的是我吗？
You think it's me you degrade now,
不是的
but it's not.
是你自己
It's you.
终你一生
As long as you live
你会因此而觉得羞辱和不洁
you will feel degraded and defiled by this.
你
You.
动手吧
Get on with it.
受够了吗？
Have you had enough?
继续
Continue.
你想要我怎么做？
What do you want me to do?
我不知道
I don't know.
随便你 把她的脸割下来
Do something. Cut off her face.
动手
Do it.
伊希斯女神保护我 伊希斯女神保护我
Mother Isis protect me. Mother Isis protect me.
起来
Get up!
起来 起来
Get up! Get up!
- 你干什么呢？- 走
- What are you doing? - Go!
走
Go!
我不是动物
I am not an animal!
I am not a fucking animal!
兄弟…
So, brother...
越来越冷了 天马上就要黑了
It's getting cooler. Be dark soon.
也许应该宿营了
Good time to set up camp, maybe.
你要宿营你就去 我是不会停下来的
You may camp if you want. I'm not stopping.
你还会说话呀
So you can still talk.
我还以为你忘记怎么说了呢
Thought maybe you'd forgotten how.
该说的时候我自然会说 现在又没什么好说的
I talk when I need to. There's nothing to say.
还在生我的气？
Still angry with me, then?
没有
No.
好吧
Yes, well, listen.
我就直说了吧 关于内奥比…
I'll get to the nub of it. About Niobe...
她怎么了？
What of her?
我在社团说的关于我和她的事情
What I said back in the collegium about me and her,
我没有… 我们从来没有过
I never... we never.
我那么说只是要激怒你 仅此而已
I only said it to make you angry. That's all.
我说的是实话 你知道的
That's the truth, and you know that.
我知道
I know.
如鲠在喉 不吐不快
Had to be said.
即使我有那个念头… 当然我决不会有…
- Even if I wanted to - which I didn't
她也不是那种女人
she's not that type of woman.
我了解女人 她不是那种人
I know women, and she's not that type.
狗日的伊万德乘人之危
Yon cunt Evander took advantage.
也许你听了会好受些
If it's any consolation,
在我结果他之前 着实教训了他一番
I gave him a right session before I killed him.
他叫得像杀猪一样
Screamed like a stuck pig.
很好 谢谢
Good. Thank you.
你之前看过蓄奴营吗？
You ever seen one of these slave camps?
没有
No.
你不会喜欢的
It's not pretty.
他们肯定已经面目全非了 你的孩子
They'll be different now, the children.
我知道
I know.
我估计你还是不清楚
I don't think you do, though.
等你到了那儿就知道了
You can't unless you've been there.
我看到的那些情景…
The things I saw...
不管怎么说 他们肯定和原来不一样了
Anyroad, they'll be different.
- 你要有心理准备 - 我不在乎他们现在什么样子
- You should be ready. - I don't care what they're like.
我只是…
I just...
想要他们回到我身边
want them back.
我的意思是…
All I'm saying is...
你最好不要太激动 呃？
best be gentle.
我会的
I will.
那个男孩呢？
And the boy?
卢西尔斯？
Lucius?
你不是想要杀了他吧？
You're not thinking of killing him, are you?
为了我的荣誉 他必须死
Honor demands that he die.
没错 这话在理 荣誉的需要
True. Fair enough. Honor demands it.
如果你真的要杀他 你的两个女儿
Most likely won't sit well with the girls though,
肯定会看不下去的
if you do kill him.
你说得太多了
You talk too much.
人无完人
We all have our faults.
屋大维打胜了？
Octavian won?
的确如此
He has.
安东尼和他的残余部队撤退到山里面去了
Antony and the remains of his army have retreated to the mountains.
他们俩都还好吗？
Are they both unharmed?
屋大维很好
Octavian is very well.
安东尼也还活着 具体情况就不清楚了
Antony's alive, but we know no more than that.
您弟弟会带着军队凯旋
Your brother will return with his army.
月底前就会回来
He'll be here within the month.
军队？还带着军队回来干嘛？
With his army? Why with his army?
政治需要
Politics.
他想告诉您 不管以后发生什么事情
He wants you to know that whatever happens in the future,
他会一直保护您
he will always protect you.
但您必须接受他的保护和忠告
But you must accept his protection and his advice.
他可真是慈悲为怀
That's very kind of him.
我向他宣誓效忠 他就会保护我？
He will look after me after I swear him my allegiance?
我又不是他的士兵
I am not one of his soldiers.
我敢肯定他不是对您有丝毫怀疑
I'm sure he does not doubt you.
我想他是要把这层意思转达给您母亲
I think he means you to convey the same message to your mother.
最好是由您来转达
Better it comes from you.
是啊 也许如此
Yes. Probably so.
您弟弟对您没有丝毫恶意
Your brother means you only the best.
否则的话 就不会派我来送信了
If it were otherwise, I would not deliver the message.
我是宁死也不会伤害您的
I'd sooner die than cause you pain.
那我要祈祷你长命百岁了
I hope you live a long life, then.
我…
I...
恕我冒昧 我有些话不吐不快
If I may, I am compelled to speak.
自从我见过您之后 我的灵魂就备受煎熬…
Ever since I met you, my soul has burned...
呃 我弟弟吃地还好吗？
So is my brother eating properly?
除非有人逼他 他是不会让自己饿着的
He would starve himself unless someone forces him to eat.
是啊 是啊
Yes. Yes.
军队的伙食合他的胃口
Army food agrees with him.
他虽然说不上敦实 但确实吃得很好
He's not stout exactly, but, yes, eating properly.
刚才的事情 我很抱歉
Sorry. Sorry about just now.
实在是无心之过
I very expressly did not mean to do that.
不知怎么就脱口而出了 写在信上也许更适合
I blurted it out anyhow. I should've written a letter.
无论如何 非常抱歉
Anyhow, sorry.
没必要道歉
There's no need to apologize.
我弟弟的朋友 也就是我的兄弟
Any friend of my brother is my brother also.
当然 等我们进一步了解之后
I'm sure when I know you better
我们会成为好朋友的
we shall be good friends.
您真是宅心仁厚
That's most gracious of you.
我实在是太过分了
A horrid imposition on my part.
您都不怎么了解我 真荒谬
Of course, you barely know me. Ridiculous.
奥克塔维娅 我正到处找你呢
Octavia, I've been looking for you everywhere.
玛尔库斯·阿格里帕 你怎么到这里来了？
Marcus Agrippa, what are you doing here?
母亲
Mother.
- 屋大维… - 哦
- Octavian... - oh
不 他没事 他没事
No, it's all right. It's all right.
他平安无事 他…他打赢了
He's unharmed. He won.
安东尼被打败了
Antony was defeated.
逃到北方去了
He's fled north.
真是好消息 太让人吃惊了
This is wonderful news. Amazing.
当然 我也怀有希望 不过没想到是这么个结果
I had hopes, of course, but I hardly expected this.
太好了
Wonderful.
希尔提乌斯合潘撒怎么样？
What of Hirtius and Pansa?
战死了
Dead in battle.
死了？
Dead?
太不幸了
That's unfortunate.
不管怎么说 确实是一场大胜
Still, a great victory.
继续念
Read on.
他的军队？
His army?
他要带军队回罗马？为什么？
He's bringing his army to Rome? Why?
他在罗马并没有敌人 要军队作甚？
He has no enemies in Rome. Why bring his army?
我只是个传信的
I am just a messenger.
我相信 等凯撒回来之后 他会很乐意告诉你的
I'm sure when he arrives, Caesar will be happy to tell you.
他自称凯撒
Caesar, he calls himself.
另一个凯撒
Another Caesar.
正是我们所需要的
Just what we need.
他称自己为凯撒 是因为他有那个正当的权利
He calls himself Caesar because that is his name by right.
是啊 是啊 毫无疑问
Yes, yes, no doubt.
老天 年轻人的野心真让我吃不消
Gods, I'm so tired of young men and their ambitions.
身心疲惫
So tired.
我可以向您保证
I assure you,
他的心里只有共和国的利益
he has only the interests of the Republic at heart.
我相信他是那么认为的
I'm sure he believes that.
我年轻的时候也是这么想的
I thought the same when I was a young man.
但这些都是浮云
But it is all vanity, you know.
过眼烟云
All vanity.
就是这里
This is the place.
让我来说话
Let me do the talking.
你好 朋友
Salve, friend.
能告诉我们代管人的办公室怎么走吗？
Can you point us in the direction of the procurator's office?
你们有何贵干？
What do you wanna know him for?
生意上的事
Business.
在找几个逃奴
Looking for some runaways.
哦 你们是奴隶猎手？
Slave catchers, are you?
差不多吧
Something like that.
这里不接待未经邀请的访客
Camp's closed to unauthorized visitors.
是吗？
That right?
捉拿逃奴赏金丰厚
Good bounty on runaways.
如果让你们进去 你们肯定会捞到不少好处
Be worth something to you, I expect, letting you in.
听着 垃圾…
Listen to me, you little weasel...
我的朋友有点吝啬 但我们都是生意人
My friend's a thrifty one, but we're all men of commerce.
你老板在哪边？
Which way is the boss man?
转过弯 一直走 那房子的门是红色
Round the bend, straight on, house with a red door.
别管他了
Oh, leave off!
他已经死了
He's bloody dead!
解开他吧
Uncouple 'em!
不是说了让我交涉嘛
Told you I should do the talking.
狗杂碎
Grunt scum.
兄弟 在这里 你的唾沫都干得比别的地方快
Your spit dries fast here, brother.
还是省着点吧
Best to save it.
驾
Come on!
你就是管事的？
You the man in charge?
要买还是要卖？
Buying or selling?
泰特斯·波罗 卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
Titus Pullo, Lucius Vorenus.
我们是来缉拿逃跑的奴隶的 据说被卖到你的营地了
Here to retrieve some runaways. Heard they got sold to your camp.
- 两个女孩 - 还有个男孩
- Two girls. - And a boy.
有他们的文书吗？
Got papers for 'em?
- 没带在身上 - 购买契约呢？
- Not with us. - Bill of sale?
也没有
No.
两个士兵出来找小妞 是吧？
Two soldiers out for some young cunny, yes?
闭上你的鸟嘴
Shut your fucking mouth.
等等 等等
Hold. Hold.
他是不是有毛病？
What's his problem?
我本来不想说的 但是…
I didn't want to have to go into this, but...
这几个孩子
these children are the private property
是盖乌斯·凯撒·屋大维的私人财产
of Gaius Caesar Octavian himself.
他很喜欢他们一大清早 把早点端到他床前
He likes to have them serve morning biscuits in bed.
特别是那个男孩 明白了吗？
Especially the boy. Got it now?
你可真下流 还挺会编故事
Oh, that's ripe. Good story.
看见印章了吗？
You see this seal?
他命令我们找回他的奴隶
His orders for us to come find his slaves.
这是什么 水獭？
What is it, an otter?
那是该死的狮身人面兽 凯撒的标记
It's the fucking Sphinx. Mark of Caesar.
- 这个封腊倒是挺奇怪的 - 穆提那的泥土
- Odd wax, this. - Mud from Mutina.
所以我的这位朋友战袍还没脱
That's why my friend here is in fighting kit.
就直接从战场上赶过来了
Straight from the battlefield.
十万火急
It's that urgent.
凯撒 是吗？
Caesar.
凯撒
刚刚战胜马克·安东尼的这位
The one who just beat Mark Antony.
你觉得他会如何对付胆敢违抗他的人呢？
What do you think he'd make of a little fellow like you who crosses him?
你说的都有道理
Yes, that's all very well,
但如果你是在说谎呢？
but what if you are lying to me?
你是说我在说谎？
Are you calling me a liar?
看看花名册
Check the rolls.
女儿…
Daughter...
是我
it's me.
是你父亲
It's your father.
你们不是奴隶猎手
You're not slave catchers.
- 她在哪儿？- 嗯？
- Where is she? - er?
另外一个
The other one.
我女儿在哪儿？
Where's my daughter?